Hasan Mahmood Aminul Islam

Metsälinnunreitti 2 F 061, Espoo 02660, Finland

Phone: +358 50 354 2958; email: hasan02.buet@gmail.com

Introduction

A successful innovative research-oriented professional with 10+ years of professional experiences in low level software development, system architecture, IoT in both Academia and Industry combined with a very strong educational background in Computer Network, Network Protocols, Distributed system and Data communication, and Future Internet.

The link of my profile: My Linkedin, <u>DBLP</u>, and Researchgate Profile

Employment History

Nokia Specialist, SoC Software (5G)

Espoo, Finland July 2019 – Dec 2021

Job Responsibilities:

- Implementing l1low device driver both in user and kernel spaces for 5G
- Verification of device driver by flashing the images in FPGA board.
- Release the Software with new features.
 - Implementation Language: C/C++,
 - Google Test Framework
 - Yocto build considering minimal linux for the verification.

Master's Thesis worker, Nomadic Lab

Jorvas, Finland October 2011 – July 2012

 $^{\prime}~L~M~Ericsson~AB$

- Investigation and Analysis of Real-time Collaboration on World Wide Web (RTCWeb) peer-to-peer data channel connections between Web Browsers
- The main focus was integrating RTCWeb data channel in the Webkit Network protocol stack
 - Open Source Userland Stream Transmission Control Protocol stack (userland SCTP), Webkit, Mozilla Firefox, GStreamer framework.
 - Key Technologies: Objective C, Node JS, Javascript.
- Worked with the IETF experts of RTCWeb

Doctoral candidate, Distributed and Pervasive Systems Group Dept. of Computer Science, Aalto University

Espoo, Finland 2013 – 2018

During the period of my doctoral studies:

—Disruption tolerant Information Centric Networking

- Perform cutting edge research in Information Centric Networking (ICN) for Delay/Disruption
 Tolerant network (DTN) and Internet of Things (IoT) and publish results
- Design, implement, and evaluate new proposals towards disruption tolerant ICN and ICN in IoT network

—Publish/Subscribe based ICN in IoT (EU funded H2020 ICT project POINT)(Best Demo Award in ACM ICN 2017 [5])

- Collaboration with several Industry and Academia
- Design, implement, and experiment with a system architecture providing IoT network services through ICN network
- A gateway based approach which connect user endpoint running IP based CoAP protocol via ICN operator network.
 - Gateway Implementation Language: C.

- Considers CoAP, CoAP observe extension, and CoAP Group communication
- Implemented a minimal version of CoAP implementation to translate CoAP messages to ICN messages and vice versa following RFC 7252 (CoAP), RFC 7641 (CoAP observe), and RFC 7390 (CoAP group communication).
 - Implementation Language: C++
 - Virtualization: Mininet
- Build IoT test network which consists of the following:
 - Nucleo boards with ELLi Ethernet NIC
 - Operating System: RIOT

The project code is released publicly in Github:

https://github.com/point-h2020/point-3.0.0/tree/master/apps/coap

Disruption Tolerant ICN

- Design and implement protocol stack for disruption tolerant ICN and Device-to-Device (D2D) communication utilizing the open source reference implementation of Content Centric Networking and Delay Tolerant Networking.
- Evaluate the above protocol stack using **ONE Simulator**
 - Implementation Language: Java
 - Result extraction using *Python* script and graph utility *gnuplot*
 - Implemented Information Centric DTN routing in One Simulator to evaluate the protocol stack.

Education

Aalto University

Ph.D., Dept. of Computer Science

Espoo,Finland

Feb. 2013 - Nov. 2018

- Major in the field of Telecommunications Software.
- Dissertation: Information Centric Networking for the Challenged Internet

University of Helsinki

Master of Science in Computer Science with distinction

Helsinki, Finland

Sept. 2010 - Feb 2013

- Major in Distributed System and Data Communication.
- Thesis: Analysis of RTCWeb Data Channel Transport Options.

Bangladesh University of Engineering Technology

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science and Engg., CGPA:3.62/4

Dhaka, Bangladesh Feb. 2003 – Jan. 2008

Project Experiences

Projects in Doctoral Studies:

 Andro Task Scheduler, Mobile System Programming Project, Aalto University: Implementation Language: Android, SQLight.

A calendar application in which an user can store his 'To Do(s)' and can view the tasks in either one of the following three views: day view, week view or month view.

The project code can be found in $\underline{\text{Task Manager}}$

- **Publish/Subscribe IoT:** The key responsibility was designing and implementing publish/subscribe based IoT on top of UDP.

Implementation Language: C.

- Indoor Positioning using Bluetooth: The key responsibility was designing and implementing a prototype of indoor positiong system using Bluetooth.

Key Technologies: Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE).

Device: BLE enabled mobile device, Arduino, BLE shield.

Projects in M.Sc:

- Distributed System Project :
 - Consistency implementing vector clock and causal multicast in distributed environment. Implementation Language Java
 - Multitier Architecture and the Web web-based calculator both in server-based version and in a version where some of the functionality is migrated on client side. *Implementation Language*JavaScript, PHP
- BrowserSocket CodeCamp BrowserSocket is a protocol called WebSockets which was introduced in the IETF and W3C to simplify and optimize bi-directional, long-lived connections between the server and the user's browser. We implemented a tic tac toe game utilizing this protocol.

Implementation Language: JavaScript

Projects in Bachelor Studies:

- 4-bit microprocessor design and experiment using CircuitMaker and then build up the design containing ALUs, counters, registers, and 1K ROM under the term project of the course of Digital System Design.
- Implementation of Unix File System an efficient and flexible file system for UNIX operating system was implemented. In this project all basic data structures of UNIX file system e.g., inode, super block, boot block etc. were used. The system was implemented using programming language C under the course named Operating System.
- Implementation of Unix Memory Management System A Dynamic Memory Manager was implemented by programming Language C for Unix System capable of allocating and releasing variable size block and splitting and merging of distributed block dynamically.

Skills

Internet Technologies: Network protocols, system architecture integration Programming Language: C/C++, Java, Python(basic), Objective C(basic)

Simulation Tools: ONE simulator

Publication

- [1] Hasan M.A. Islam, Dmitrij Lagutin, Antti Ylä-Jääski and Nikos Fotiou; "Transparent CoAP Services to IoT Endpoints through ICN Operator Network". Journal of Sensors MDPI 2019. (impact factor 3.576).
- [2] Hasan M.A. Islam, Dimitris Chatzopoulos, Dmitrij Lagutin, Pan Hui and Ylä-Jääski; "Boosting the Performance of Content Centric Networking using Delay Tolerant Networking Mechanisms". IEEE Access, 2017 (Impact factor 3.367).
- [3] Hasan Islam, Dmitrij Lagutin and Nikos Fotiou. "Observing IoT resource over ICN". IFIP Networking conference and Workshops, IFIP (workshop paper), June, 2017.
- [4] Hasan M.A. Islam, Dmitrij Lagutin, Andrey Lukyanenko, Andrei Gurtov and Antti Ylä-Jääski; "CIDOR: Content Distribution and Retrieval in Disaster Networks for Public Protection". The 13th IEEE International Conference on Wireless and Mobile Computing, Networking and Communications, October, 2017.
- [5] Nikos Fotiou, George Xylomenos, George C. Polyzos, **Hasan M.A. Islam**, Dmitrij Lagutin, Teemu Hakala and Eero Hakala; "ICN enabling CoAP Extensions for IP based IoT devicess". 4th ACM Conference on Information-Centric Networking, September 2017 (Demo), (Best Demo Award).
- [6] Hasan M.A. Islam, Andrey Lukyanenko, Sasu Tarkoma and Antti Ylä-Jääski; "Towards Disruption Tolerant ICN". The 20th IEEE Symposium on Computers and Communication (ISCC), July, 2015.
- [7] Nikos Fotiou, Hasan Islam, Dmitrij Lagutin, Teemu Hakala and George C. Polyzos. "CoAP over ICN". 8th IFIP International Conference on New Technologies, Mobility and Security (NTMS), 2016, pages 1-4.
- [8] Afroze, T., Sarkar, S., Islam, A, Rahman, A.; "More stable Ad hoc On-Demand Distance Vector Routing Protocol". 4th IEEE conference on Industrial Electronics and Application, 2009. ICIEA 2009. pages 150-155.